O.W. Riegel Papers WLU.Coll.0387
Washington and Lee University, James G. Leyburn Library Special Collections and Archives
- Propaganda, 1912-1992; 12.58 Linear Feet 7 large storage boxes, 2 oversize boxes, and 3 other boxes (Box 1-16, Folder 1-466)
  - Inter-War Period, 1918-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7-70)
    - Publications, 1919-1939 (Box 1, Folder 48-69)
      The publications in the Riegel papers from the interwar period show the shift in American focus from the economy to international relations from the early 1930s to 1939. The early publications focus on the impact of New Deal programs with only some regard to events outside the U.S. Publications from the late 1930s have a heavily international perspective with pictoral booklets of the atrocities in the second Sino-Japanese war, and threats of German fascism. Academic articles relate to the press, particularly in China, but also from a global perspective, Modern propaganda techniques, and international relations. Finally, there is a sampling of newsletters focusing on the same topics from various perspectives.
      - Publications, 1926-1933 (Folder 48)
      - Publications, 1934 (Folder 49)
      - Publications Jan.-May, 1934 (Folder 50)
      - Publications Jun.-Sep., 1934 (Folder 51)
      - Publications, 1934-1935 (Folder 52)
      - Publications, 1936-1937 (Folder 53)
      - Publications, 1937-1938 (Folder 54)
      - Publications, 1938-1940 (Folder 55)
      - Academic Articles, 1932-1935 (Folder 56)
      - Academic Articles, 1936-1938 (Folder 57)
      - Academic Articles, 1919-1939 (Folder 58)
      - Academic Articles Chinese Press, 1935-1937 (Folder 59)
      - Academic Articles Chinese Press, 1937-1938 (Folder 60)
      - Academic Articles Chinese Press, 1938 (Folder 61)
      - Broadcasting, 1932-1936 (Folder 62)
      - Broadcasting, 1936-1938 (Folder 63)
      - Broadcasting, 1938 (Folder 64)
      - The French Say, 1934-1938 (Folder 65)
      - The French Say Miscellaneous, 1919-1939 (Folder 66)
      - Kiplinger Washington Letter, 1932-1939 (Folder 67)
      - Virginia Press Asociation, 1932-1939 (Folder 68)
      - Miscellaneous, 1919-1939 (Folder 69)
    - Miscellaneous, 1919-1939 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 71-74)
    Items in this subseries related to the Spanish Civil War primarily consist of propaganda leaflets and publications on both sides of the conflict, highlighting the opposing sides' atrocities and how they will ensure the values and freedom of the Spanish people.
    - Leaflets, 1936-1939 (Folder 71)
    - Leaflets, 1936-1939 (Folder 72)
    - Leaflets, 1936-1939 (Folder 73)
    - Publications, 1936-1939 (Folder 74)
  - World War II, 1939-1945 (Box 2-4, Folder 75-279, Box 5-6, Box 1-5, Box 11, Oversize 1)
    Items in this subseries are related to the World War II era in both of the main theaters of war. Some items of note include propaganda leaflets in a variety of languages including German and Japanese, documents from various government agencies including the Office of War Information, and some ephemeral materials used as propaganda during the war.
    - Correspondence, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 75-91)
      Riegel's corresepondence in this series primarily relates to those he worked and interacted with during his time with the Office of War information. One topic of particular interest to Riegel was the "Strzetelski Affair" which focused on the contested censorship of a Polish news agency and their description of troop position in the eastern front.
      - All-Bor, 1939-1945 (Folder 75)
      - Ber-Car, 1939-1945 (Folder 76)
      - Cha-Day, 1939-1945 (Folder 77)
      - Far-Gal, 1939-1945 (Folder 78)
      - Gre-Kir, 1939-1945 (Folder 79)
      - Larson, 1939-1945 (Folder 80)
      - Las-Loo, 1939-1945 (Folder 81)
      - Markham, 1939-1945 (Folder 82)
      - Nee-Smi, 1939-1945 (Folder 83)
      - Strzetelski Affair Sep. 14-17, 1943 (Folder 84)
      - Strzetelski Affair Sep. 18-22, 1943 (Folder 85)
      - Strzetelski Affair Sep. 23-Misc., 1943-1945 (Folder 86)
      - W, 1939-1945 (Folder 87)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1941 (Folder 88)
      - Miscellaneous, 1942-1943 (Folder 89)
      - Miscellaneous, 1944-1945 (Folder 90)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1946 (Folder 91)
    - Domestic Propaganda, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 92-97, Box 14, Folder 462-466)
      Riegel's collection of domestic propaganda during the second World War highlighted appeals to the working class by the Germans to stand against "big business" interests, and the pro-peace movement primarily through a series of drawings by Pola Clair.
      - Domestic Propaganda, 1935-1938 (Folder 92)
      - Domestic Propaganda, 1939-1940 (Folder 93)
      - Domestic Propaganda, 1941-1942 (Folder 94)
      - Domestic Propaganda, 1941 (Folder 95)
      - Domestic Propaganda, 1941 (Folder 96)
      - Domestic Propaganda, 1939-1945 (Folder 97)
      - WAC Recruiting and War Bonds, 1942-1946 (Box 14, Folder 462)
      - WAC Recruiting and War Bonds, 1942-1946 (Box 14, Folder 463)
      - WAC Recruiting and War Bonds, 1942-1946 (Box 14, Folder 464)
      - WAC Recruiting and War Bonds, 1942-1946 (Box 14, Folder 465)
      - WAC Recruiting and War Bonds, 1942-1946 (Box 14, Folder 466)
    - European Leaflets, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 98-112)
      European propaganda leaflets, in Riegel's collection, show the various appeals by different groups to persuade the enemy to surrender. While most of the leaflets are addressing a German audience, there are some in Hungarian, Polish, and Arabic aiming to persuade at least a tacit support for the allies. The leaflets are sorted based on their identification number often found on one of the corners of the leaflet.
      - AG20-USG30, 1939-1945 (Folder 98)
      - WG2D-WG18k, 1939-1945 (Folder 99)
      - WG19-WG22s, 1939-1945 (Folder 100)
      - Office of War Information Planning: Mediterranean area, 1944-06-14-1944-12-06 (Box 2, Folder 97a)
        O.W. "Tom" Riegel's copy of an official "confidential" binder distributed to staff of the United States Office of War Information detailing propaganda objectives for the Mediterranean region of Europe for 1944, specifically the countries of Albania, Bulgaria, Greece, Romania, Yugoslavia, Italy, and Hungary.
      - WG23-XH22, 1939-1945 (Folder 101)
      - ZG60-ZG70, 1939-1945 (Folder 102)
      - ZG71-ZG81, 1939-1945 (Folder 103)
      - ZG82-ZH2, 1939-1945 (Folder 104)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 105)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 106)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 107)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 108)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 109)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 110)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 111)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 112)
    - European Newsletters, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 113-134)
      These newsletters were disseminated by allied forces to citizens of liberated countries. These newsletters, ranging from Dutch to Flemish to French often described events on the front lines and encouraged readers to support the war effort.
      - Carta de America Mar.-Dec., 1944 (Folder 113)
      - Catholic Bulletin, 1944 (Folder 114)
      - Clip Sheet May-Sep., 1944 (Folder 115)
      - Clip Sheet Sep.-Nov., 1944 (Folder 116)
      - English Catholic Newsletter, 1944 (Folder 117)
      - The Flying Dutchman Feb.-Sep., 1944 (Folder 118)
      - The Flying Dutchman Sep-Oct.., 1944 (Folder 119)
      - The Flying Dutchman Oct.-Nov., 1944 (Folder 120)
      - The Flying Dutchman Nov. 2-13, 1944 (Folder 121)
      - The Flying Dutchman Nov. 14-30, 1944 (Folder 122)
      - The Flying Dutchman Dec., 1944 (Folder 123)
      - The Flying Dutchman Miscellaneous, 1944 (Folder 124)
      - Frontpost, 1944 (Folder 125)
      - Letter from America Feb.-Mar., 1944 (Folder 126)
      - Letter from America Sep.-Oct., 1944 (Folder 127)
      - Letter from America Oct.-Dec., 1944 (Folder 128)
      - Per Avion, 1944 (Folder 129)
      - Spiritual Issues of the War, 1944 (Folder 130)
      - The Times, 1944 (Folder 131)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1944 (Folder 132)
      - Miscellaneous, 1944 (Folder 133)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 134)
    - Government Reports, 1939-1945 (Box 2-4, Folder 135-232)
      Riegel's collection of government reports center around the effectiveness in developing and implementing propaganda addressed to the Axis powers and neutral and liberated countries. Reports tend to focus on one aspect of propaganda ranging from understanding the target audiences culture, to forms of counterpropaganda used by enemy forces.
      - Board of Economic Warfare, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 135-139)
        Reports by the Board of Economic Warfare were periodically issued detailing the economic situations of various parts of the world and their relation to the front lines. This gave allied forces an idea of available resources for themselves and their enemies looking forward.
        - Board of Economic Warfare Jun.16-18, 1942 (Folder 135)
        - Board of Economic Warfare Jun.19-22, 1942 (Folder 136)
        - Board of Economic Warfare Jun.23-25, 1942 (Folder 137)
        - Board of Economic WarfareJun.26-27, 1942 (Folder 138)
        - Board of Economic Warfare Jun.-Jul., 1942 (Folder 139)
      - Bureau of Overseas Publications, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 140-143)
        The Board of Overseas publication analyzed published issues in other countries, aiming to understand the literary and media culture of different nations to improve propaganda efforts. Some analysis includes reports on Japanese war songs and european perspectives on American elections.
        - Bureau of Overseas Publications, 1943-1944 (Folder 140)
        - Bureau of Overseas Publications, 1944 (Folder 141)
        - Bureau of Overseas Publications, 1944-1945 (Folder 142)
        - Bureau of Overseas Publications Miscellaneous, 1944-1945 (Folder 143)
      - Bureau of Public Relations, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 144-146)
        The Bureau of Public Relations focused on ensuring positive relations with neutral and liberated countries during the war effort. Some of its material, found in this sub-series include Public Relations officer guidelines and foreign censorship codes.
        - Bureau of Public Relations, 1942 (Folder 144)
        - Bureau of Public Relations, 1944 (Folder 145)
        - Bureau of Public Relations Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 146)
      - Congressional Record, 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 147-148)
        Segments from the congressional record found in this subseries focuses on the mobilization and deployment of troops between 1939 and 1945.
        - Congressional Record, 1943 (Folder 147)
        - Congressional Record, 1945 (Folder 148)
      - Coordinator of Information, 1942 (Box 2-3, Folder 149-160)
        Riegel maintained a collection of documents from the Coordinator of Information office. These documents pertained to ongoing events in the second World War and their relation to propaganda. Some documents focus on the handling of news and claims by the Axis powers, the surrender of a british fleet to the Japandese, and the presence of allied forces near Singapore.
        - Coordinator of Information Feb. 7-12, 1942 (Folder 149)
        - Coordinator of Information Feb. 13-18, 1942 (Folder 150)
        - Coordinator of Information Feb.19- Mar.2, 1942 (Folder 151)
        - Coordinator of Information Mar.3- Mar.11, 1942 (Folder 152)
        - Coordinator of Information Mar.-Apr., 1942 (Folder 153)
        - Coordinator of Information Apr. 22-27, 1942 (Folder 154)
        - Coordinator of Information Apr.-May, 1942 (Folder 155)
        - Coordinator of Information May-Jun., 1942 (Folder 156)
        - Coordinator of Information Jun., 1942 (Folder 157)
        - Coordinator of Information Miscellaneous, 1942 (Folder 158)
        - Coordinator of Information Miscellaneous, 1942 (Folder 159)
        - Coordinator of Information Miscellaneous, 1942 (Folder 160)
      - Federal Communications Commission, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 161-163)
        Riegel's items from the Federal Communications Commission primarily relate to its reports on radio broadcasts. Included in their reports are recommendations for foreign radio propaganda, and their prioritization of national defence in their own decisions.
        - Federal Communcations Commission, 1941-1942 (Folder 161)
        - Federal Communications Commission Feb.-May, -1942 (Folder 162)
        - Federal Communications Commission Jun.- Nov., -1942 (Folder 163)
      - Motion Picture Bureau, 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 164)
      - Office of Control, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 165-167)
        Riegel's documents related to the Office of Control highlight the emphasis on censoring foreign media to ensure support of the allied troops. some items of note include breif correspondence related to the censorship of individual broadcasts due to lack of documentation, and periodic reports of the publications of various radio broadcasts.
        - Office of Control, 1942 (Folder 165)
        - Office of Control, 1942-1943 (Folder 166)
        - Office of Control, 1944 (Folder 167)
      - Office of Public Opinion Research, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 168-169)
        The Office of Public Opinion Research focused on the public mood of various events during the war. Some items in this subseries include an analysis of public opinion as it relates to FDR's public talks and speeches, and public opinion of naval war policy.
        - Office of Public Opinion Research Sep., 1941 (Folder 168)
        - Office of Public Opinion Research Oct., 1941 (Folder 169)
      - Office of War Information, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 170-184)
        Riegel worked with the Office of War Information durring the Second World War. His role was to provide guidance, analysis, and propose various forms of propaganda to use against enemy forces and to persuade potentially friendly neutrals. Items in this subseries are heavily related to these subjects and report on the successes and failures of implemented propaganda.
        - Office of War Information, 1942 (Folder 170)
        - Office of War Information Jan.-Feb., 1943 (Folder 171)
        - Office of War Information Feb.-Nov., 1943 (Folder 172)
        - Office of War Information, 1943-1944 (Folder 173)
        - Office of War Information Jun., 1944 (Folder 174)
        - Office of War Information Jul.-Sep., 1944 (Folder 175)
        - Office of War Information Sep.-Oct., 1944 (Folder 176)
        - Office of War Information Oct.-Nov., 1944 (Folder 177)
        - Office of War Information Nov., 1944 (Folder 178)
        - Office of War Information Nov.-Dec., 1944 (Folder 179)
        - Office of War Information, 1945 (Folder 180)
        - Office of War Information Apr.-Sep., 1945 (Folder 181)
        - Office of War Information Miscellaneous, 1942-1945 (Folder 182)
        - Office of War Information Miscellaneous, 1942-1945 (Folder 183)
        - Office of War Information Miscellaneous, 1942-1945 (Folder 184)
      - O.I.C., 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 185)
      - Outpost Service Bureau, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 186-192)
        The Outpost Services Bureau provided support to govenrment agencies in ensuring their ability to function via connecting them with lines of communication and providing support when necessary. They created monthly progress reports of various outpost stations reporting the status of these stations and their effectiveness.
        - Outpost Service Bureau, 1942-1943 (Folder 186)
        - Outpost Service Bureau, 1943-1944 (Folder 187)
        - Outpost Service Bureau May 23-24, 1944 (Folder 188)
        - Outpost Service Bureau May-Jul., 1944 (Folder 189)
        - Outpost Service Bureau Jul.-Sep., 1944 (Folder 190)
        - Outpost Service Bureau Oct., 1944 (Folder 191)
        - Outpost Service Bureau Oct.-Dec., 1944 (Folder 192)
      - Psychological Warfare Branch, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 193-200)
        Items from the Psychological Warfare Branch focus on the impact of propaganda and counter propaganda on the target audeinces. Reports in this subseries include an analysis of propaganda upon French citizens, and a booklet on the functions of the 5th Army propaganda team.
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Feb., 1942 (Folder 193)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Feb.-Mar., 1942 (Folder 194)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Mar.-Apr., 1942 (Folder 195)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Apr.-May, 1942 (Folder 196)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch, 1943-1944 (Folder 197)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Jan.-Feb., 1945 (Folder 198)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Mar.-Jul., 1945 (Folder 199)
        - Psychological Warfare Branch Miscellaneous, 1942-1945 (Folder 200)
      - State Department, 1941-1946 (Box 3, Folder 201-202)
        Riegel's items from the state department primarily relate to the status of various areas in the front lines of the second World War. Some documents in this subseries inculde a description of the status of press and radio in Vichy France, and Chiang Kai Shek's perspective on the Japanese war front.
        - State Department, 1941-1944 (Folder 201)
        - State Department, 1944-1946 (Folder 202)
      - Radio Conference of Cairo, 1939-1945 (Box 3, Folder 203-204)
        The two documents in the Radio Conference of Cairo subseries are full text copies of the radio agreements describing acceptable and unlawful use of the radio in attempts to influence populations beyond a nation's borders.
        - Radio Conference of Cairo, 1938 (Folder 203)
        - Radio Conference of Cairo, 1938 (Folder 204)
      - United States Information Service, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 205-206)
        Documents in this subseries detail the efforts made by the USIS to inform foreign peoples about the United States and its values through various publications. Some examples in this subseries include the report of the effectiveness of an Italian agazine and guidelines for foreign magazine publications.
        - United States Information Service May- Jun., 1945 (Folder 205)
        - United States Information Service Jun.-Jul., 1945 (Folder 206)
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Box 3-4, Folder 207-232)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939 (Folder 207)
        - Miscellaneous Feb.-Nov., 1941 (Folder 208)
        - Miscellaneous Mar.-Dec., 1941 (Folder 209)
        - Miscellaneous, 1942 (Folder 210)
        - Miscellaneous Mar.-Apr., 1942 (Folder 211)
        - Miscellaneous Apr.-Aug., 1942 (Folder 212)
        - Miscellaneous Aug. 25-28, 1942 (Folder 213)
        - Miscellaneous Aug.-Sep., 1942 (Folder 214)
        - Miscellaneous Sep.-Oct., 1942 (Folder 215)
        - Miscellaneous Oct.-Dec., 1942 (Folder 216)
        - Miscellaneous, 1942-1943 (Folder 217)
        - Miscellaneous, 1944 (Folder 218)
        - Miscellaneous May-Nov., 1944 (Folder 219)
        - Miscellaneous Dec., 1944 (Folder 220)
        - Miscellaneous, 1945 (Folder 221)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 222)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 223)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 224)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 225)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 226)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 227)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 228)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 229)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 230)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 231)
        - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 232)
    - Japanese Leaflets, 1939-1945 (Box 4, Folder 233-242)
      Riegel's collection of Japanese leaflets consist of two aspects: US made leaflets issued to the Japanese and Japanese made leaflets issued to the U.S. Both use persuasive techniques to convince soliders to surrender or cease fighting, showing there is greater value in being at home than on the front lines. U.S. propaganda tended to appeal to the futility of the Japanese effort, showing how U.S. progress was steady in spite of their resistance. Japanese propaganda tended to emphasize that the profits of the war were directed to a non-fighting elite, and that family members would prefer the soldier's presence at home to their death at war. The leaflets are sorted by their identification numbers found on one of the leaflet's corners.
      - 2-J-1--16-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 233)
      - 17-J-1--25-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 234)
      - 26-J-1--101-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 235)
      - 103-J-1--123D-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 236)
      - 134-J-1--139-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 237)
      - 144-J-1--148-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 238)
      - 150-J-1--152-J-1, 1941-1945 (Folder 239)
      - Miscellaneous, 1941-1945 (Folder 240)
      - Miscellaneous, 1941-1945 (Folder 241)
      - Miscellaneous, 1941-1945 (Folder 242)
    - Newspapers, 1940-1944 (Box 4, Folder 243)
    - Notes, 1939-1945 (Box 4, Folder 244-250)
      Riegel kept assorted notes about a variety of topics including the Camera Club at Washington and Lee, Descriptions for his future autobiography, political details in Mexican History, and information related to coworkers, staff, and events during his time at the Office of War Information.
      - Notes, 1938-1940 (Folder 244)
      - Notes, 1941-1942 (Folder 245)
      - Notes, 1942-1943 (Folder 246)
      - Notes, 1943-1944 (Folder 247)
      - Notes, 1944-1945 (Folder 248)
      - Notes Miscellanoeus, 1938-1945 (Folder 249)
    - Personal Affects, 1939-1945 (Box 4, Folder 251-262)
      Items in this subseries were the personal belongings of Oscar Riegel after the second World War. Some items include his material as an official air raid warden, in the event of a domestic air raid, financial statements on purchases, war ration books, and programs from events he attended.
      - Air Raid Warden, 1941-1942 (Folder 251)
      - Air Raid Warden Miscellaneous, 1940-1945 (Folder 252)
      - Finances, 1941-1942 (Folder 253)
      - Finances May-Aug., 1942 (Folder 254)
      - Finances, 1942-1944 (Folder 255)
      - Finances Miscellaneous, 1941-1944 (Folder 256)
      - Government Items, 1941-1945 (Folder 257)
      - Government Items, 1941-1945 (Folder 258)
      - Leisure, 1941-1944 (Folder 259)
      - Leisure, 1944-1946 (Folder 260)
      - Leisure Miscellaneous, 1941-1946 (Folder 261)
      - Miscellaneous, 1940-1946 (Folder 262)
    - Press Releases, 1939-1945 (Box 4, Folder 263-270)
      Press releases in this subseries give a description of headlines during the Second World War. Topics of note include Hitler's invasion of Poland, the Psychological effect of paratroopers, and the Finnish impact on the Eastern Front.
      - Press Releases, 1939 (Folder 263)
      - Press Releases Jan.-May, 1940 (Folder 264)
      - Press Releases, 1940-1941 (Folder 265)
      - Press Releases Jan.-May, 1942 (Folder 266)
      - Press Releases, 1942-1943 (Folder 267)
      - Press Releases Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 268)
      - Press Releases Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 269)
      - Press Releases Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Folder 270)
    - Publications, 1939-1945 (Box 4, Folder 271-279)
      Publications in this subseries tend to focus on propaganda analysis, the warfront, and radio communications. Some items of note in this subseries include the code of the National Association of Broadcasters and commentary on the Bill of Rights.
      - Publications, 1938 (Folder 271)
      - Publications, 1939 (Folder 272)
      - Publications Jan.-Mar., 1940 (Folder 273)
      - Publications Apr.-Dec., 1940 (Folder 274)
      - Publications, 1940-1941 (Folder 275)
      - Publications, 1942-1945 (Folder 276)
      - Publications, 1945 (Folder 277)
      - Publications, 1938-1945 (Folder 278)
      - Publications, 1938-1945 (Folder 279)
    - Ephemeral Materials, 1939-1945 (Box 5-6, Box 1-5)